<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: News | Spring in Practice]]></title>
  <link href="http://springinpractice.com/blog/categories/news/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://springinpractice.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-22T13:16:48-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://springinpractice.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Willie Wheeler]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Spring in Practice now available]]></title>
    <link href="http://springinpractice.com/2013/05/08/spring-in-practice-now-available/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-08T23:42:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://springinpractice.com/2013/05/08/spring-in-practice-now-available</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://springinpractice.s3.amazonaws.com/blog/images/sip_on_shelves.jpg" alt="SiP at Barnes &amp; Noble" /></p>

<p>Spring in Practice is now available!</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s also the Deal of the Day today, which means half off if you buy it today (May 8, 2013) from Manning. Use code <strong>dotd0508au</strong> at <a href="http://www.manning.com/wheeler/">www.manning.com/wheeler</a>.</p>

<p>Josh and I hope that everybody enjoys the book. It was a lot of work, but I&rsquo;m very happy with the end result.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Combined my two blogs]]></title>
    <link href="http://springinpractice.com/2012/05/05/combined-my-two-blogs/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-05T14:39:30-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://springinpractice.com/2012/05/05/combined-my-two-blogs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>To better focus my Java/Spring blogging, I&rsquo;ve merged my former Wheeler Software blog into this one. There are a few articles that didn&rsquo;t make the cut, but the majority of them did.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Zkybase now supports authorized access to GitHub via Spring Social GitHub]]></title>
    <link href="http://springinpractice.com/2012/03/06/zkybase-now-supports-authorized-access-to-github-via-spring-social-github/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-06T04:04:45-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://springinpractice.com/2012/03/06/zkybase-now-supports-authorized-access-to-github-via-spring-social-github</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This one&rsquo;s another quick <a href="https://github.com/williewheeler/zkybase">Zkybase</a> screenshot post. Using <a href="https://github.com/SpringSource/spring-social-github">Spring Social GitHub</a>, it&rsquo;s easy to access public user and repo information via the <code>GitHubTemplate</code>. But if we want to access private information, or write capabilities, we need to use the <a href="http://projects.spring.io/spring-social/">Spring Social</a> connection framework. This involves adding a Spring Social web controller to the app, giving users a way to log into Zkybase itself (via <a href="http://projects.spring.io/spring-security/">Spring Security</a>, and then finally giving them a way to connect their Zkybase account to their GitHub account via OAuth 2.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Screenshots</h2>

<p>Here&rsquo;s what the GitHub section of the account page looks like before you connect to GitHub:</p>

<p><img src="http://springinpractice.s3.amazonaws.com/blog/images/2012-03-06-zkybase-now-supports-authorized-access-to-github-via-spring-social-github/disconnected.png" alt="Disconnected screenshot" /></p>

<p>Once you&rsquo;ve done that, the display changes to the following:</p>

<p><img src="http://springinpractice.s3.amazonaws.com/blog/images/2012-03-06-zkybase-now-supports-authorized-access-to-github-via-spring-social-github/connected.png" alt="Connected screenshot" /></p>

<p>And now we can perform various secure operations on our GitHub objects, like viewing repo hooks:</p>

<p><img src="http://springinpractice.s3.amazonaws.com/blog/images/2012-03-06-zkybase-now-supports-authorized-access-to-github-via-spring-social-github/hooks3.png" alt="Hooks screenshot" /></p>

<p>I plan to use this integration to support autoprovisioning continuous integration servers, among other things.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re interested in the code itself, please see my blog post entitled <a href="http://springinpractice.com/2012/03/06/using-spring-social-github-to-access-secured-github-data-code/">Using Spring Social GitHub to access secured GitHub data</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[More Zkybase screenshots]]></title>
    <link href="http://springinpractice.com/2012/01/17/more-skybase-screenshots/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-17T13:30:03-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://springinpractice.com/2012/01/17/more-skybase-screenshots</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s been a little while since I&rsquo;ve posted <a title="Zkybase GitHub site" href="https://github.com/williewheeler/zkybase">Zkybase</a> screenshots, so here&rsquo;s the work in progress. I explain how to implement this stuff (<a title="Spring Data Neo4j" href="http://www.springsource.org/spring-data/neo4j">Spring Data Neo4j</a>, <a title="Spring/GitHub integration" href="https://github.com/SpringSource/spring-social">Spring/GitHub integration</a>, <a title="JavaScript InfoVis Toolkit" href="http://thejit.org/">JavaScript InfoVis Toolkit</a>, etc.) in chapter 11 of my book <a title="Spring in Practice" href="http://manning.com/wheeler/">Spring in Practice</a> (Manning).</p>

<h2>App overview page</h2>

<p><img src="http://springinpractice.s3.amazonaws.com/blog/images/2012-01-17-more-skybase-screenshots/app_overview.png" alt="App overview" /></p>

<p>Applications are a central concept in Zkybase. This is how the app overview page looks so far. (It&rsquo;s just a start.) The concept behind it is that if you want a 360-degree view of an app (dev view, test view, release view and ops view), you come to the app details page and then you can start looking at different views.</p>

<h2>App repository commits page</h2>

<p><img src="http://springinpractice.s3.amazonaws.com/blog/images/2012-01-17-more-skybase-screenshots/commits.png" alt="Commits" /></p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a repo commit history for a given app. Right now it&rsquo;s just integrated with GitHub, but the idea is to provide integrations with other providers too (e.g. BitBucket).</p>

<h2>App repository watchers page</h2>

<p><img src="http://springinpractice.s3.amazonaws.com/blog/images/2012-01-17-more-skybase-screenshots/watchers.png" alt="Watchers" /></p>

<p>Again, an app details view. This time it&rsquo;s GitHub watchers for a given app repo.</p>

<h2>Region details page</h2>

<p><img src="http://springinpractice.s3.amazonaws.com/blog/images/2012-01-17-more-skybase-screenshots/region.png" alt="Region" /></p>

<p>Visualizations are one of the more exciting features that a CMDB can offer. One of the huge advantages of putting your configuration management data in a database is that you can move away from Visio documents and Gliffy diagrams, and move instead toward data modeling and automatically generating views. Here I&rsquo;m using the <a title="JavaScript InfoVis Toolkit" href="http://thejit.org/">JavaScript InfoVis Toolkit </a>library to generate an interactive graph visualization. It is a great complement to the underlying <a title="Neo4j" href="http://neo4j.org/">Neo4j</a> graph database.</p>

<h2>Automation view</h2>

<p><img src="http://springinpractice.s3.amazonaws.com/blog/images/2012-01-17-more-skybase-screenshots/xml.png" alt="XML" /></p>

<p>This might strike you as a strange screenshot, but in reality it&rsquo;s an example of the most important view&mdash;the automation view. The main reason we want to manage configuration data in a database is that we can build web services (Zkybase supports both JSON and XML views) that simultaneously drive automation and human-consumable views of the sort that a support team would use.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Zkybase/GitHub integration]]></title>
    <link href="http://springinpractice.com/2012/01/14/skybasegithub-integration/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-14T07:55:43-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://springinpractice.com/2012/01/14/skybasegithub-integration</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A major goal for <a title="Zkybase GitHub site" href="https://github.com/williewheeler/zkybase">Zkybase</a> is to tie together the activities of developers, testers, release engineers and operations. A few major benefits are:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Tool integration:</strong> We can single source app lists and more across development, build, test, deployment, monitoring, knowledge management and other tools.</li>
<li><strong>Process streamlining:</strong> Outputs from the dev process feed into the test and deployment processes, which in turn feed into operational processes.</li>
<li><strong>Communications across teams:</strong> All the teams work from the same concepts and data, facilitating communication.</li>
</ul>


<p>One of the first things I want to tackle in Zkybase, then, is supporting some developer-centric concerns. An important one is source control. Obviously Zkybase isn&rsquo;t itself a source control management system, but it makes sense to pull in useful information from the source code repos just to provide a &ldquo;single pane of glass&rdquo; where developers and other users can get a holistic view of what an app is all about.</p>

<p>Since I&rsquo;m using GitHub, Github integration is a logical starting point for Zkybase/SCM integration. GitHub has a <a title="GitHub REST API" href="http://developer.github.com/v3/">REST API</a> that makes this integration easy. I wrote a <a title="Calling the GitHub API using Spring’s RestTemplate" href="http://springinpractice.com/2012/01/14/calling-the-github-api-using-springs-resttemplate/">post</a> that explains the technical approach. Here&rsquo;s the end result:</p>

<p><img src="http://springinpractice.s3.amazonaws.com/blog/images/2012-01-14-skybasegithub-integration/skybase_scm4.png" alt="Zkybase SCM page" /></p>

<p>I suspect that such integrations will be a large part of the value that Zkybase delivers. They will help realize the process, tool and communications benefits I highlighted above.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
